Sweeney, Dorothy L.; Papers mss135
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Dorothy L. Sweeney Papers
1941-2004
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Sweeney, Dorothy L., 1923-
mss135
0.66 cubic ft.
Dorothy (nee Langley) Sweeney graduated from St. Mary's Institute in Amsterdam, New York in 1941. After graduation, Sweeney accepted an office position at General Electric in Schenectady. In her off hours she spent time at WGY, GE's AM radio station, where her brother Edward Langley acted and wrote for the station's dramatic productions. She later worked at WGY and in radio in New York City. Sweeney provided sound effects for several programs and her scripts from this work form the bulk of this collection.
The materials are located onsite in the department.
Biographical / Historical
Dorothy Sweeney (nee Langley) was born in Amsterdam, N.Y. in 1923. After graduating from high school in 1941, she worked as a secretary at General Electric in Schenectady, N.Y., where her brother Edward was an actor on WGY, G.E.'s AM radio station. When WGY's sound effects artist was drafted later that year, Dorothy was hired to replace him.
After two years at WGY, Dorothy Sweeney moved to New York City and enrolled at the Radio and Television Institute to pursue a professional career in sound effects. In January 1944, she was hired at WOR, the Manhattan-based flagship station of the Mutual Broadcasting System. She worked at WOR until 1946, when she married returning serviceman John Sweeney and returned to Amsterdam to raise a family. In 2004 Sweeney was interviewed by Professor Ivan Steen of the University at Albany's Oral History Program.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains scripts and memorabilia related to the broadcasting career of Dorothy Sweeney. Dorothy Sweeney's career as a sound effects artist at WGY and WOR is represented by a number of scripts from programs on which she worked. These scripts are typically marked up with pen or pencil to indicate sound cues. Programs represented include crime and detective dramas such as Nick Carter and The FBI in Action, horror stories such as The Strange Doctor Weird and The Sealed Book, and World War II propaganda programs such as John Smith: American and The People vs. Adolf Hitler. A set of WOR promotional photographs show Sweeney demonstrating how she uses various household objects to create sound effects. Memorabilia includes several radio trade magazines, a 1945 technical manual on the creation of sound effects, and Sweeney's New York City pistol license, which she maintained so that she could fire blanks during the recording of action sequences. The series also includes cassettes and transcripts of Sweeney's 2003-2004 interviews with the University at Albany Oral History Project.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2004 from Dorothy Sweeney and Professor Ivan Steen.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Separated Materials
Archivists transferred the following title: Radio Sound Effects by Joseph Creamer and William B. Hoffman to the book division of Special Collections. The catalogue records for this monographs will be included in the University Library Catalog.
Radio scripts; Sound recordings; Schenectady County (N.Y.); Radio stations; Radio and Television Broadcasting; Sweeney, Dorothy l., 1923-
- Anniversary Program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1943; 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Count of Monte Cristo, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "The Creation" from God's Trombones, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Day of Reckoning, Council for Democracy: "The People vs. Adolf Hitler", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Extra, Extra, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- FBI In Action, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- FM Playhouse, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- FM Playhouse, 1942 January-1942 August (Box 1, Folder 9)
- FM Playhouse, 1942 September-1942 October (Box 1, Folder 10)
- FM Playhouse, 1942 November-1942 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
- FM Playhouse, 1943 January-1943 March (Box 2, Folder 12)
- FM Playhouse, 1943 April-1943 November (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Interview with Dorothy Sweeney (Copy), 2003 December 12 (Cassette 1)
- Interview with Dorothy Sweeney (Master), 2003 December 12 (Cassette 2)
- Interview with Dorothy Sweeney (Copy), 2004 January 15 (Cassette 3)
- Interview with Dorothy Sweeney (Master), 2004 January 15 (Cassette 4)
- Ivan Steen Oral History Transcript, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- John Smith - American, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- The Mysterious Traveler: "Concerts of Death", 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- News Clippings, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Nick Carter, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Police Department of New York, Pistol Licenses, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Photographs, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Radio Row, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- The Sealed Book, ca. 1944 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Special Army Scripts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Station WOR Identification Card, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
- The Strange Doctor Weird: "The Voice of Death", 1945 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- To the President: "The Special Day", 1943 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Tune In, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 27)